Britain's historic royal palaces have
provided a backdrop to a bloody struggle
for power for almost a thousand years.
Within the bricks and mortar, beneath
the plaster and the layers of paint, are
the tales of power, politics, intrigue,
and revolution that have held this
country in their grip for a millennium.
Once a reigning monarch no longer has
need for a palace, it may be eligible to
join the exclusive club [music] of
historic royal palaces earmarked for
conservation forever.
While the queen retains ownership of the
buildings, [music]
the palaces receive no funding from
either the monarch or the government.
They're paid for by tourists having a
nice day out. So, the more visitors,
[music] the better. Ah, if only life
were that simple.
>> [music]
>> Hampton Court was Henry VIII's power
base, the beating heart of TUDA,
England.
These days, it attracts half a million
visitors a year.
The Chapel Royal [music] is one of the
most popular places in the palace. The
best vantage point is from the king's
private balcony known as the Royal Pew.
But recently, the pews had more than a
monarch to contend with. [music]
Yesterday, the balcony was subjected to
60 members of a tour party, [music] and
overnight a large crack has appeared in
the paneling beneath.
Surveyor Amanda [music] White has been
called in.
>> Well, I had a call from the chaplain and
a call from our security staff and they
said, "Oh, the paneling is opening up.
Come quickly."
Dust was just raining down literally on
on the visitors. [music] So, uh, we
thought we better attend to it. There's
obviously a gap. Something's finding its
way through.
>> Closing key parts of the palace will hit
visitor numbers and income. Amanda's
hoping her engineers can address the
problem without turning visitors away.
>> Visitors generate the funds that we so
desperately need to maintain these
buildings, but we have to balance it
very carefully. Otherwise, we run the
risk of them actually causing some of
the damage that we then have to address.
This building has been here for many
hundreds of years and it seems to be a
little unhappy at the moment. So, we
just need to find out why and um try and
sort it out really.
>> You never wake at 3:00 in the morning
for fear that your palace is falling
down. Oh, quite regularly [laughter]
I wake up and worry about all the things
I haven't done and all the things I need
to do. [laughter] I think that's normal
though, isn't it?
[music]
The chapel has been in continuous use
for over 450 [music] years. It was built
for Cardinal Woolseie before Henry VIII
added its most famous feature, the
finest TUDA fan vaulted ceiling [music]
still standing.
Sir Christopher Ren added the screen and
the Victorians [music] added some golden
stars for good measure. The old place
has taken the knocks and [music] bears
them well. But it's taken 21st century
tourists to really make the cracks
[music] begin to show. Amanda will have
to wait for the engineers report before
she'll know if it's possible [music] to
complete the repairs without turning the
public away.
Early in the morning, before the first
visitors have begun to arrive, David
Hows is turning up for work.
He has given his professional life to
the study [music] of dust. Latest
research has shown that dust is far more
than a nuisance. It actually corrods the
precious historic artifacts at an
alarming rate. This is another problem
brought in by the [music] allimportant
visitors. Most of the dust is actually
from the fibers from their clothes. So
the more visitors you have, the more
dust is brought into the palace.
[snorts] There are two ideas how we
could reduce the amount of dust. Of
course, one is just to let people roam
around the palace naked or in those
allin-one suits you see in nuclear power
stations. But if we're trying to create
an ambiance of sort of historical
authenticity, this may be slightly
distracting. In the precious hours
between sunrise and the arrival of the
first members of the public, David
trolls the corridors and the great halls
in search of his arch enemy, Dust.
[music]
On a day like today, when the sun is
coming through the window, you can
actually see the dust floating in the
air. And this dust will slowly deposit
on objects and and cause damage. And
someone's got to come along afterwards
and remove the dust from the objects and
thereby doing more damage. [music] Some
of the most fragile objects are the vast
tapestries specially commissioned to
hang in this very room by Henry VII.
Though dust [music] and light have
reduced the original threads of shining
silver to dull brown, the effect is
still stunning.
These tapestries when they were first
made, each one individually was worth uh
the same amount of money as one of Henry
VII's finest battleships. So in modern
terms, you're thinking about the cost of
an aircraft carrier, I guess. So you're
talking about the equivalent of millions
and billions of pounds. And the surface
of these tapestries is incredibly
fragile. So, of course, any physical
operation that you do on the surface of
the tapestries is inevitably going to
cause some damage.
[music] And David has spent many early
mornings contemplating the problem.
>> It's always a privilege to come around
the palace when it is empty and [music]
there aren't any people. It does feel as
though you have a sense of ownership of
it that you know that maybe the [music]
general public get an idea of. But
working here is is different.
To work [music] out which objects are
most at risk from dust, David has
devised a cunning system. He lays glass
slides in [music] strategic locations to
catch dust particles. Then he returns
the slides to the lab and lets his
invention take [music] the strain. A
microscope linked to a computer counts
every speck and never complains. Now
David's [music] gadget is nominated for
a conservation Oscar.
I've [music] been shortlisted and the
judges are going to come and visit me
fairly shortly. So hopefully, fingers
crossed, you know, this may be a winner.
>> Amanda has had the report from the
engineer and the royal pew has been
closed to the public. Inside, Amanda's
team have begun the dramatic task of
dismantling the 450y old structure,
starting by lifting the floor.
We're now having to fight the bullets
and go ahead and take it out, but we're
being as careful as we can. Um, and
hopefully there won't be too much
damage, but we really do now need to see
just what's going on.
>> The seemingly brutal treatment of the
chapel should mean it soon begins to
give up its secrets. Amanda has also
been keeping a secret, but today at
last, the truth is out.
>> I will shortly be leaving historical
palaces. I will be leaving um in a
little over 3 weeks. Um moving on to uh
English Heritage. So I have an awful lot
to do between now and then. There I'm
involved in an awful lot of projects.
Some very small, some quite extensive.
This one is growing seemingly by the
week and day in fact. So I will need to
need to be handing over a number of
things to to my colleagues.
>> So Amanda has only a very short time to
get to the bottom of the chapel's
problems.
While Hampton Court struggles to cover
its costs, the real money is made in
another historic palace, the Tower of
London. This is Britain's most visited
historic building, attracting over 2
million visitors every year. The tower
was built by William the Conqueror
shortly after his victory at the Battle
of Hastings as a palace and a signal to
the people of London that they were
indeed conquered. But it was the
fanatical castle builder Edward I who
built the gateway known as the Bwood
Tower 200 years later as part of a
complex and impregnable ring of outer
defenses.
Anyone wishing to enter the tower in
[music] Edward's time would have had to
pass over a drawbridge into the
semic-ircular lion tower, pass under a
pork cullis across a narrow walkway
before being confronted [music] by a
second pork cullis in the bwood tower.
the true front door and only entrance to
the mighty Tower of London.
Today, the Bowa Tower is still the
principal entrance for every visitor.
But there are problems and the gate has
been closed to the public.
The 700year-old building is starting to
crumble, posing a risk to both the
future of the tower and the public who
pass below. Tracy Simmons has the task
of assessing the problem.
Hopefully, we're going to do the whole
lot the the east and the west elevation.
So, it would be one complete scaffold.
>> Yeah.
>> Huge job and huge cost actually on the
project.
We're losing original material. So, we
need to do the repairs to prevent us
losing any more of the original fabric.
So that that's the most important
thing part of the project.
>> And to ensure the money is available to
preserve the fabric of the buildings,
Historic Royal Palaces aims to make them
as entertaining as possible.
>> Costume guides are among the most
popular attractions.
>> No, they are to go with the fine
gentleman yonder.
>> Well, you manage the business here at
you have a halbert and he does not. I
think it gives you some right.
>> What do you good people? What sort of
man do you think I'm What sort of
character? A good character, sir. Not a
bad character. What character might I
be?
>> Historic Royal Palaces has just awarded
Europe's largest contract for running
costume guides to Mark Wallace of past
pleasures.
>> Fellow, you drunken fellow. Dressing up
in costume is sexy. There's no way
around it. It is showbiz. Of course,
we're pretending. It is roleplay in a
sense. It's acting. We're not those
people. We can't possibly know much
about this much, you know. So, our job
is to try and get across to the public
this much that we know about those
people in those times. The
>> fact you
doesn't scare you. He's a bold fellow,
isn't he?
>> People come to these buildings for a
sense of the past, for a sense of
understanding how they were used.
Costume interpreters are a tremendous
draw to bring the buildings alive and to
tell the human story behind the bricks
and mortu.
>> It isn't just a matter of dressing up
because the guys have to stay in
character all the time they're in
public. They have to attend regular
classes in the department and etiquette
of the times
>> status, but also know how to move in
those clothes. Which means, let's do a
practical thing for the state. Up you
get, and let's get you how to bow in
curtsy. Now, Rosie, I know that you
already know this. So, would you show
Dorothy how to curtsy as a lady of the
17th century?
>> But it's mostly that bit.
>> For years, I thought actors would be the
best people to do this because you'd
expect that to be the case. Then I found
on the whole your average actor wants a
script and a stage and there's
[clears throat] no script and there's no
stage. The whole place, if you like, is
a stage. So then I thought, well,
perhaps I need badged up academics,
serious historians. The trouble with
that is they would know their history,
but again, generalization, they wouldn't
be comfortable dressed up. You have to
feel confident in the way that an actor
will, but using the brains as a teacher.
So, we're not one thing or the other.
We're a nice sort of mange of all those
good bits.
>> It's simply a matter of bending your
knees just like this.
>> All the dancing masters told you for
hundreds of years, you must imagine
there's an invisible string holding your
head to the ceiling, so you can't wobble
your head around. If you came to court
in the best possible dress, the best
possible gown, you'll think you look the
cat's meow. But your movements might
betray you. They might think, "Oh, she's
very well-dressed, but she's clearly
someone from the country, a provincial,
doesn't know how to move by moving ahead
around or by laughing out loud." A loud
laugh betrays the vacant mind.
>> See, you're both way. If we have an
agenda, it's to honor our ancestors who
came before us to show people nowadays
in the 21st century that they weren't
stupid cuz they wore funny wigs or
walked in a certain way.
>> Back at the Bwood Tower, there's bad
news for Tracy.
>> Well, what does it look like? It's in a
It is in a mess. One of the biggest
problems I think is their flashings are
just pinned and so water's getting
behind and there's a lot of failure at
the heads of the windows and the top has
completely failed. Probably about an
inch of rot into the surface quite a
lot. Timbers have been replaced.
>> Those sections would have to be
replaced.
>> Though the specialist surveyor has
examined the building, Tracy's keen to
see the problem for herself.
>> What area? I think if you go and have a
look at that panel
>> up in that one and you can see the the
problem with the um the sills as well
with the flashing gun sills.
>> For Tracy, the main concern is to get
work underway before winter reeks more
damage on the historic gateway. From a
distance, [music] there doesn't seem to
be too much to worry about, but a closer
inspection of the old building reveals
problems that need urgent attention.
>> [music]
>> Unless it's repaired soon, then the
deterioration speeds up and and [music]
you know decay will take place on a much
bigger scale. Some immediate repair
works need to be carried out.
>> Feel quite sad now. Yes.
>> It's in a bit of a sorry state stage.
>> It is, isn't it? Yeah.
>> Yes. It's I mean from this side you can
see there are problems but it's it's not
until you actually get above it you see
the the extent of the
>> a couple of bits. Tim I put my hand out
and then quickly pulled it back cuz it's
like really fragile.
>> Yes. Yes.
>> I'm just wondering if it's going to stay
out there for another winter. [snorts]
>> Back in Mark Wallace's rehearsal, the
boys are about to take a bow. We'll see
what's the least unnatural thing you can
do and then I'll show you what it should
be.
>> I I pretended to go with the other hand
to be perfectly honest and just
>> perhaps
>> straight dismissed from court.
[laughter] The fella's a fish monger and
you sir who you're just a country booby
show. [laughter]
We get all this stuff from the dancing
masters and from the manuals, the
etiquette books that tell the aspiring
middle class how to move like the
gentry. So if I see company approaching,
I shall step forward, transfer the stick
to there. Off goes the hat to the side
like this and then down. Keep the cane
parallel with the leg. That way you
don't trip someone over and it's it's
elegant. So same thing. I'm talking to
the ladies. I see Lord Lord Booby
coming. He owns most of the shop
but he's a dull dog. I see him. Up goes
the hat. I've already transferred the
cane without knowing I did it to the
side showing the inside of the hat. And
then then down. Give that a go.
He holds his hat like a cabbage.
>> [laughter]
>> Thank you.
>> Sorry.
>> It's not It's not sturdy.
>> No, it's not. [laughter]
>> You provided me with
>> inferior goods.
>> That's what your That's what your
customers say of your shop. My lord,
[laughter]
>> you'll see on stage people doing
historical bowing and they do this sort
of stuff, which is nonsense. Some people
did that, but they were meant to be
laughed at by the contemporary audience.
>> Good, good, good. All right, that's
[applause] it.
>> [music]
>> The Tower of London is the only historic
royal palace that makes money. [music]
In a competitive world, it's important
that the newly contracted costume guides
are accurate, entertaining, and a hit
with the paying public.
>> Laugh at me.
>> I'm afraid that's an occupational.
>> The latest thinking is that 2 million
visitors every year should leave with
more than photographs. They should leave
with stories.
>> Now the guard, thinking that he might
have reached shots, falls upon the floor
anyway and allows the robbers to rush
straight past him. So that is the story
of how the crown jewels almost [music]
came to be stolen, but eventually were
recovered to be placed on show in the
jewel house for you to see today. Thank
you very much. The past made flesh to
pull in more eager history [music]
hunters. And no one enjoys British
history quite like the Americans.
Since 9/11, the palaces have seen a
[music] downturn in visitor numbers.
John Barnes is the director of
conservation. He sees how the pounds
come in and decides how the pounds go
out.
>> Those of us who rely upon the tourist
trade are finding it a very tough time.
projects that we thought were going to
go ahead this year. I think we're going
to have to move some of them off to next
year. The biggest of the ones that I
think we're going to have to defer
>> is the byword, which is one of the big
gateways into the tower garden.
>> These are the projects that these
conservation projects are the ones that
excite us and we want to do
>> the next one to do this and move on.
>> Yeah. And that's always
>> we had hoped to carry out a next phase
of work on it this autumn and winter. I
really think given the value of it, we
ought to move that backwards into next
year.
>> Being cancelled,
>> it's a tough decision, but for Tracy,
it's a personal blow.
>> It's disappointing. We enjoy doing the
conservation projects. That's why we
work for historic royal palaces. So,
it's disappointing.
Do you take it personally?
>> Um, I know it's not not aimed at me
personally, but when you work so hard on
a project, there is part of you that
does feel that it's personal.
>> All is quiet in the royal chapel.
The latest theory is that the royal pew
may be suffering from rot caused by
rainwater getting in from the roof
above.
Amanda is on the case.
Oh dear.
>> You're going to have limited headroom in
there. Nice
catwalk fashion. I'm a slave to it.
We're roughly above where the main body
of the chapel
>> meets the uh raw pew here. There have
obviously been problems here with this
particular bay of lead. Historically,
we've got a welded lead patch here, and
we think that that water has more
recently been passing through underneath
here. It's starting to fail.
>> It's time for what might be the most
unusual view in Hampton Court. Amanda
has been joined by Lee Proser and
Adrienne Gibson. They are experts in
architecture and like nothing better
than an unexplored roof space.
>> I'm trying to see what what can be seen
really at this point, but it's it's
quite a tight space. There's a lot of
wood over here.
>> Another glamorous job.
>> Yeah. Non-stop glamour. We get to wear
all the latest fashions and come to the
most wonderful places.
>> Here comes the next Norwegian soldier.
>> Who needs glamour?
Where are you?
>> I'm coming over.
>> Oh, sorry. Hang on. I'm going to come
back a bit.
>> Okay,
>> back a bit.
>> You can squeeze through that. I'm just a
bit conscious that two of us.
Nearly went right. You now need to
squeeze yourself through that gap
through the chapel structure. Can you
see?
Where's the labor pen when we need it?
>> I've got it in my pocket.
>> Oh, look good. You're wearing a paper
suit.
>> I can see some lovely tuna brick work.
>> Oh,
I'm glad we've eaten lunch. Are you
stuck?
>> How am I supposed to get out? [laughter]
>> Carefully.
You laughed at the paper suits earlier.
[laughter]
>> When it comes to old buildings, Adrien
is the man. If water's causing rot,
Adrienne's all smelling nose will have
spotted it.
>> Amanda was worried there was a area of
white and whether it was fungal attack.
It is not
>> right.
>> It is simply dried out old resin and in
fact
>> naturally coming out the wood
>> out the wood and there are in fact
bubbles of solid resin
>> resin.
>> So there's no fungal attack that I have
seen purely insect attack.
>> Insects. Okay.
>> Yeah. which is uh far easier to manage.
If it was fungus, you would smell it. I
mean, I've got a pretty sensitive nose
and there's no smell of fungus at all.
Just plain dirt.
>> Very sweet.
>> Plain dirt, but not a fungus smell.
Absolutely sure. There's no attack by
fungus.
>> Good.
>> Don't want to do any more reading until
my hands are clean.
>> The dance veil,
>> but it stops now. [laughter]
>> And then coming around the corner off.
>> No, I think this is it down to ground.
Your wife's going to wonder where you've
been today.
>> Oh, it's all right. She's quite
>> Is this normal?
>> The strange secret world of Hampton
Court's roof is Amanda's favorite part
of the palace, but it's revealed no
fungal attack, and Amanda is no closer
to solving the riddle of the cracked
royal pew, and her time has run out.
>> Being up on the roof today, it was
fantastic. And I was thinking, I'm never
going to be up here again. And as I came
down one of the turrets, and I've I
spent quite a long time in turrets in my
time here. um various monitoring
exercise we've been doing and I was
thinking I'm probably never going to do
this again ever um and that's quite sad.
>> It's the day of the conservation Oscars,
but David has a problem.
>> It's a bit of a disaster cuz I've packed
the wrong suit. This one's a bit tight.
So, I'm going to phone up Julie to see
if she can bring [laughter]
a suit in from home.
>> Does it look ridiculously small? No.
Sure.
>> Try doing it up.
>> I won't do it up. [laughter]
>> I can't believe it.
The nerve-wracking thing is I know that
if by chance I have won the award, I
will have to say some words. And I
always get very nervous when I say
anything in public. Although I really
enjoy doing it, but uh I always get
terrible stage fright before I have to
stand up and say something,
especially as I don't want it to be
boring.
[music]
David is keen [music] to get to the
British Library early to put his display
up before the great and the good
assemble for the prestigious prize
giving.
[music]
I think we can now [music] go for a cup
of coffee. I hope that's not all the
soft drinks after the event as well.
They said no alcohol. That's deeply
worrying. [music]
[music]
[music] These are like
[music] Yeah.
It's the moment of decision at the
conservation Oscars.
>> It's my pleasure today to announce the
winner of the best completed program of
research and or development aimed at
furthering the practice of conservation.
Congratulations to David Hull and the
Historic Royal Palace's textile
conservation studioing the 2004 Anna
Plouden Award.
[applause]
But unlike their Hollywood counterpart,
the conservation awards have no time for
dusty speeches, thanks and tears of joy.
>> Thank you very much for allowing us to
secure in [applause] our competition. I
hope you read it.
>> Excellent.
>> Excellent. Thank you.
>> I wasn't allowed to say anything.
>> So, what did you have prepared in your
speech that you didn't make?
>> I got lots of jokes. I was going to
thank the 2,700,000
visitors for coming to Historic Royal
Palaces, bringing all their dust with
them and making the project necessary. I
had my list, you see, like this and I
was going to read and I say I'd like to
thank the 2,762,000
visitors to historic Royal Palace
individually.
Alice Arv.
>> That was my joke.
and it's lost forever.
>> What started off as a crack in the royal
pew is a right royal mess, but it will
have to be someone else's problem. It's
Amanda's final day.
>> It's a big mess, but it's very much an
organized mess, so to speak. Um, most
certainly that it's going to get worse
before it gets better. Um, and I'll be
leaving that in the capable hands of of
someone else.
It will be very neat and tidy by the
time I go today. I need to organize
that. But mess probably about sums it up
at the moment.
>> But the unraveling [music] problems
being unexpected, unbudgeted, and
expensive.
The investigations [music]
could now go on for a year, during which
time the royal pew must remain closed.
And to pay for the work, more visitors
must be [music] attracted. more visitors
that will challenge the craft of the
TUDA architects and continue testing
[music] the old building to its limits.
And while the pros and cons of visitors
are balanced, so too are the hundreds of
[music] projects waiting to consume all
those entrance fees.
And the Royal Pew is throwing [music] a
delicately balanced budget out of
kilter.
>> We're really having to [music] find
money and we don't have that money. All
our money um has been allocated for this
financial year. It's a small pot anyway.
So to find it to continue, we will have
to take it from elsewhere, which means
something else, frankly, is going to go
out the window. Now, um that's a very
difficult decision to take because the
money this year has been allocated on a
priority basis. So,
it's a constant juggle and balancing of
priorities and and trying to to
determine the relative priority to
things that are already top priority is
very difficult and um that's not going
to be an easy job.
>> In her new job, Amanda may earn more,
but very few do these jobs for money
alone. In these palaces, the passion of
the past is everywhere. Of craftsmen, of
kings, of rebels and visionaries who
each had their moment in history. And
for many, the passion remains.
This is a place Amanda will remember.
Her place, her moment in time, and for
one last moment, her palace.
[music] Glor.
Spread
to me. [music]